Guide to the Herbert Aptheker Papers, 1842-1999, (bulk 1934-1994)
Department of Special Collections
Herbert Aptheker Papers,
1842-1999, (bulk 1934-1994)
Special Collections M1032
Aptheker, Herbert
103
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1998 and 2000.
Biography
Dr. Herbert Aptheker, historian and lecturer, was born in Brooklyn, New York, on July 31, 1915 to Benjamin and Rebecca (Komar) Aptheker. He married Fay Aptheker on Sept. 4, 1942; they had one daughter, Bettina Aptheker, an author and historian in her own right. Aptheker received his B.S. in 1936, an A.M. in 1937, and his Ph.D. in 1943, all from Columbia University. He also holds a Ph.D. (honorary) from Martin Luther U., Halle, Germany, 1966 and a DHL (honorary), University of Massachusetts, 1996.
He edited Masses and Mainstream from 1948 through 1952 and Political Affairs from 1952 through 1963. He was director of the American Institute for Marxist Studies, New York City, from 1964-1985. He was a professor at Hostos Community College, CUNY, 1971-1977, and has lectured extensively throughout the United States and Europe from 1941 through the present. He was a visiting lecturer in the Department of History at Bryn Mawr College, 1969-1971; in addition, he was a visiting lecturer at University of Massachusetts from 1971-1972, Yale University, 1976, University of California at Berkeley Law School, 1978-1991, University of Santa Clara, 1982-1983; and a visiting professor of Afro-American Studies at University of California at Berkeley, 1984.
He has written and published extensively, and is the author of To Be Free: Studies in American Negro History, 1948, rev. ed. 1992, World of C. Wright Mills, 1960, Soul of the Republic, 1964, Negro Slave Revolts in the United States, 1939, Negro in the Civil War, 1938, Nat Turner's Slave Rebellion, 1966, Mission to Hanoi, 1966, Labor Movement in the South During Slavery, 1954, The Truth about Hungary, 1957, The Nature of Democracy, Freedom, and Revolution, 1967, History of the American People, 3 vols., 1959, 1960, Essays in the History of the American Negro, rev. edit., 1964, Era of McCarthyism, 1955, Dare We Be Free?, 1960, American Foreign Policy and the Cold War, 1962, American Negro Slave Revolts, 1943, rev. edit., 1963, 1993, American Civil War, 1961, Urgency of Marxist-Christian Dialogue, 1970, Afro-American History: the Modern Era, 1971, Annotated Bibliography of the Published Writings of W.E.B. Du Bois, 1973, Early Years of the Republic, 1783-1793, 1976, The Unfolding Drama: Studies in U.S. History, 1979, Racism, Imperialism, and Peace, 1987, Abolitionism: A Revolutionary Movement, 1989, The Literary Legacy of W.E.B. Du Bois, 1989, Marxism: Demise or Renewal, 1990, Anti-Racism in U.S. History, 1992.
In addition to these original writings, he has edited numerous works, including Disarmament and American Economy, 1960, One Continual Cry, 1965, Marxism and Democracy, 1964, And Why Not Every Man, 1961, Marxism and Alienation, 1965, Documentary History of the Negro People in the United States, Vols. 1-7, 1951-1994, Marxism and Christianity, 1967, Autobiography of W.E.B. Du Bois, 1968, The Correspondence of W.E.B. Du Bois, Vol. I, 1973, Vol. II, 1976, Vol. III, 1978, The Published Writings of W.E.B. Du Bois, 40 vols., 1973-1986, Education for Black People (Du Bois), 1973, Prayers for Black Folk (Du Bois), 1980, Against Racism: 1887-1961 (Du Bois), 1985.
Aptheker ran for the U.S. Congress in 1966 as the Independent Peace candidate; he also ran for the U.S. Senate in 1976 as the Communist Party candidate. He served to major F.A. AUS, 1942-1946, ETO.
He served as a Guggenheim Fellow from 1946 to1947, and he received grants from the Social Science Research Council, 1961, the Rabinowitz Foundation, 1965, and the American Council of Learned Studies, 1974. He holds memberships in the American Historical Association and the Association for the Study of Negro Life, which awarded him its History Award in 1939 and 1969.
Scope and Content
The collection contains Herbert Aptheker's professional correspondence with other academics, Marxist scholars, as well as his correspondence from his presidency of AIMS [The American Institute of Marxist Studies] with people interested in Marxism; manuscripts, printed articles, and books written by Aptheker; family correspondence and information on the Aptheker family in general and Bettina Aptheker in particular; the research files and manuscripts belonging at one time to W.E.B. Du Bois and given to Aptheker at the time that Du Bois moved to Ghana in the early 1960's; and the manuscripts and supporting documents related to A DOCUMENTARY HISTORY OF THE NEGRO IN THE UNITED STATES, Vols. 1-7.
Access Terms
Aptheker, Bettina; Aptheker, Fay; Aptheker, Herbert; Lynd, Staughton; Washington, Booker T.; American Institute for Marxist Studies
Series Description and Container List
- Series 1. Correspondence
  Arranged chronologically by year and thereunder alphabetically. A small portion is arranged alphabetically at the end of the series.
  - Correspondence, 1934 - 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence [212], 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1943, 1944, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - International Publishers, 1946 - 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1946 - 1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Misc. correspondence & clippings, 1947 - 1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes 2 tls from W.E.B. Du Bois.
    Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - B, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Borleau, Pierre; Buchman, Harold; Buckman, Rachel [People's Victory Forum]
  - C, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Cartlett Mora, Elizabeth
  - D, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Derr, Elizabeth; Dimow, Lillian [Connecticut Committee to Aid Smith Act Victims]; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963
  - E, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Elkins, Alfreda
  - G, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Gottesman, Max; Goodman, Crockett, Eden & Robb; Government Printing Office
  - H, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Hare, Alvin; Hart, A. Richard; Harvey, Louise; Holton, John L.; Huberman, Leo; Monthly Review; Pennsylvania Civil Rights Conference
  - M, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    McCarthy, Joseph R.; Mitchell, Broadus; U.S. Senate. Subcommittee on Investigations
  - N, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Nevins, Allan; Nordholt, J.W. Schulte; Columbia University
  - P, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Patterson, William; Civil Rights Congress
  - R, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Roberts, Holland; Rudwick, Elliott Morgan; Bates College; California Labor School
  - S, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Schneiderman, Harry; Sigal, Clancy; Who's Who in World Jewry
  - T, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Thurston, John H.
  - A, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    The Afro-American; Antioch Review; The Atlantic
  - B, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Bernstein, Sam; Bickford, Jane; Bloom, A.; Brownell, Herbert; Buckman, Rachel; People's Victory Forum; Progressive Party of the District of Columbia
  - C, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Cameron, Angus; Copstein, S.A.; Cronon, Edmund D.; Cameron & Kahn Publishers; Yale University
  - D, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    D[?], Horace; Dolgow, Clara; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Dunn, Robert W.; Labor Research Council
  - E, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Evans, Gertrude; Progressive Party of the District of Columbia
  - F, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Fast, Howard; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; Foster, Bill; Rein, David; Forer & Rein, Attorneys at Law
  - H, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Harper, Fowler V.; Henry Holt & Co.; Yale Law School
  - J, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Jewsih Cultural Center, Washington, D.C.
  - K, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Kaiser, Ernest; Kaplan, Sidney; Klousky, Bob; Kurrier, C.; Univ. of Massachusetts, Amherst
  - L, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Lawson, John Howard; Lowenfels, Walter; Lincoln Educational Foundation
  - M, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Mandal, [Bernard]; Maurice, A.; McGurty, L.E.; Morley, Karen; Schwartz, Nadya B.
  - N, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Doroshkin, Sadie; Nelson, Steve; The Nation; Committee for Negro-Jewish Relations; New Jersey Law School
  - P, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Paschal, Gregory; Peffer, Nathaniel; Pike, Arthur; Pollack, R.; Presser, J.; International Union of Students, Prague; Philadelphia Forum; Pittsburgh Courier; Princeton Univ. Press
  - R, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Reddick, L.D.; Requa, Robert; Riuricov, L.T.; Roberts, Holland; Rosenblatt, Sidney; Rubin, Arthur; Atlanta University; Literary Gazette, Moscow; National Committee to Defend Negro Leadership
  - S, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Schneiderman, Harry; Shapiro, Herb; Sillen, Samuel; Swift, Nancy; Masses & Mainstream; New Foundations; Swarthmore College; Who's Who in American Jewry
  - W, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Wilkerson, Doxey; Williams, James N.; Wortis, Henry; Jefferson School of Social Sciences; National Urban League; Wisconsin Labor Youth League
  - A, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Abzug, Martin M.; Albertson, Bill; Allen, Jim; Anderson, William D.; Aoki, Haruo; Aoki Publishing Co.; International Publishers
  - B, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Includes "Commentary on the American Scene" by Herbert Aptheker, tms, 3 p.
    Berlioz, J.; Binkley, Eleanore; Bloom, A.; Bontemps, Arna; Braverman, Maurice; Brombach, Charles; Buckman, Rachel; Democratic Nouvelle, Paris; Fish University Library
  - C, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Cameron, Angus; Canright, Margery; Cardiff, Ira D.; Carter, Dyson; Casetta, Mario; Cerney, Isobel; Chapperon, Matthew; Chaleff, Lynne; Cohen, Robert; Cornforth, Maurice; Crane, Henry H.; Cronick, Jaclyn; Cameron Associates, Inc.; Liberty Book Club; Univ. of Wisconsin Labour Youth League
  - D, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Includes 3 tls from W.E.B. Du Bois, dated 1955 Apr. 18, 1955 Aug. 19, and 1955 Nov. 21.
    Daschbach, Johnny; Davis, Benjamin Jo; Davis, Beulah M.; Donner, Frank; Downer, Victor S.; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Civil Rights Congress
  - E, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - F, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Fairley, Margaret; Fast, Howard; Feldman, Eugene; Federer, Gerald; Field, Ben; Fishman, George Gurley; Forer, Joseph; Forman, Mr.; Foster, William Z.; Freyd, Bernard; Blue Heron Press; Forer & Rein, Attorneys at Law; New Frontiers
  - G, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Gauncy, Nat; Gordon, Jerry; Gore, Jack; Grant, Betty
  - H, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Hall, Micky; Heifetz, Robert; Hendley, Charles; Hunboldt, Charles; Hunton, W. Alphaeus; Antioch College; Blue Heron Press; Council on African Affairs, Inc.
  - J, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Jagan, Janet; Jaker, F.W.; Jerome, Alice; Jordan, Casper LeRoy; Wilberforce Univ.
  - K, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Kaufman, Max; Kenicki, Kikuchi; Klousky, Robert; Kramer, Harry; Kurrier, Chester; Kunitz, Hy
  - KPFA: correspondence and text of broadcasts, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - L, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Lehman, Herbert; Leith, Paul; Lesueur, Mendel; Lohr, George; Life Magazine; U.S. Senate
  - M, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Mackin, Edith; Malarch, Rene Jimenez; Maltz, Albert; Marzani, Carl; McGurly, Lawrence; McKie, Bill; NcNeil, Allan D.; Miller, Warren; Mitchell, Broadus; [Morray, J.P. ?]; Murphy, George B., Jr.; Murphy, Joyce Perry; Committee to End Sedition Laws
  - N, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Nelson, Steve; N.A.A.C.P.
  - O, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Olsen, Otto H.
  - P, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Papagos, Premier; Paradise, Jean; Pataki, Janos; Paschal, Gregory; Pettus, Tony; Platt, David; Polk, William T.; Popostru; Daily People's World; Greece; Greensboro (N.C.) Daily News; International Union of Students; Political Affairs
  - Q, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Quaye, MacGranaky
  - R, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Rainbow, Bernice; Randolph, Richard; Reddick, L.D.; Rexroth; Richmond, Al; Ritz, Leon; Roberts, Holland; Robinov, Gil; Rogow, Sally; Rossiter, Clinton; Ruchamis, Louis; Action Books; California Labor School, Inc.; City College New York; Cornell University; Daily People's World; Shaw University
  - S, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Saltzman, R.; Scales, Junius; Seeman, E.; Shigeo, Iwasaki; Sillen, Janet; Sklar, Martin J.; Sorkin, Morris; Sterling, Philip; Stover, John F.; Strack, Celeste; Citadel Press; Jewish Publication & Research Committee; Purdue University
  - T - V, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Templin, Ralph; Tratchy, [?]; Vey, Lucy
  - W, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Includes Dan Wakefield's article "Justic in Sumner: land of the free", The Nation (Oct. 1, 1955).
    Wakefield, Dan; Wallach, Irving; Waxman, Elliott; Weinberg, Annette; Woodbridge, Benjamin; Freedom of the Press Committee
  - Y - Z, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Yukiyama, Yoshimasa; Zuckerman, Abe
  - Unidentified, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - A, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Alfred, Helen; Allan, Billy; Allister, Will & Mona
  - B, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Baron, Harold; Berkeley, Adam; Bernstein, Leonard; Berry, Abner W.; Boyer, Richard O.; Boyle, Sara Patton; Brooks, Maxwell R.; Brown, Robert E.; Buckman, Rachel; Association of Social Science Teachers; Marxist Discussion Club, Queens College; Michigan State Union
  - C, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Cameron, Angus; Chakovsky, A.; Chaleff, Lynne; Chancey, Martin; Claiborne, Bob; Clark, Joe; Cohen, Bob; Cox, Oliver C.; Cameron Associates, Inc.; Daily Worker; Foreign Literature, Moscow; Lincoln University; Westin University
  - D, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Includes 1 tls from Herbert Aptheker to W.E.B. Du Bois and 1 tls from W.E.B. Du Bois to Herbert Aptheker.
    Davis, Benjamin J., Jr.; Delson, Arthur K.; Dennis, Gene; Dolson, James; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Dunn, Bob; Dweretzky, Mr.; Daily Worker; John Dewey Society of Yale University; Labor Research Association
  - E, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Einheit, Berlin; Ellingham, Lewis; Erickson, James; Evans, Gertrude; Progressive Party of the District of Columbia
  - F, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Fahnestock, Karol; Feldman, Eugene; Fischer, Toni; Fladeland, Betty; Flexnor, Eleanor; Franklin, John Hope; Frantjis, Jean H.; Frederickson, Fritz; Freistadt, Hans; Folsom, D.; Folsom, Robert; Foster, Bill; Brooklyn College; Central Michigan College; Richmond, Calif. Public Library
  - G, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Gellhorn, Ernie; Gordon, Mac; Gray, Barry
  - H, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Fedak, George; Hartz, Louis; Harvard University; Hofstra University
  - J, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Jerome, Alice; Jones, Lenna E.; Jordon, Myra; Journal of Negro History
  - K, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Kelly, Jeanie; Kilson, Martin L.
  - KPFA: correspondence and text of broadcasts, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - L, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Lefwin, Alita & Leon; Levy, Charles; Logan, Rayford; Howard University
  - M, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    Mandelblatt, Sol; Mandeehern, Robert; Martin, Riley, III; Marzani, Carl; Max, Alan; Meyers, George A.; Miles, M.G.; Mills, C. Wright; Morris, Muriel
  - N - O, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    Nelson, Steve; Olsen, Otto H.; National Guardian; New Century Publishers; New Haven (Ct.) Evening Register; New York, New Haven, & Hartford Railroad
  - P, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    Pittman, John; Platt, D.; Presser, Dr. J.; Public School 241, New York
  - R, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Reckdahl, Martha Lon; Rector, Raymond; Reddick, Dr.; Reeder, Larry E.; Roeder, Marlene; Rummery, E.E.; Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago
  - S, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    S[?], Amy; Scheer, Robert; S[?], Raymond Frederick; Schwartz, Kay; Seeman, Ernest; Selsam, Howard; Shigeo, Iwasaki; Shutz, Robert; Silver, Joe; Singletary, Otis A.; Sorkin, Morris; Stakvel, Frank D.; Stephenson, Wendell; Struik, D.J.; City College of New York; KPFA-FM, Berkeley, Calif.; University of Chicago; University of Texas
  - T, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Tiesler, Amy S.; Togai, Y.; Touchet, Francis H.
  - W, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Webster, James; Wellman, Saul; Wilkerson, Doxey A.; Williams, W.A.; Winston, Edna; Columbia University; Jefferson School of Social Science
  - Y, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Yukiyama, Yoshimasa
  - A, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Alfred, Helen; Almquist & Wiksell, Stockholm; American Socialist
  - B, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Barth, Alan; Benesch, Irving; Benson, Robert; Berg, Max; Benstein, I.J.; Bittelman, [?]; Blankenstein, Blanky; Bofman, Albert; Boshkowitz, Sarah; Buck, [?]; Buckman, Rae
  - C, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Cardiff, Ira D.; Chancey, Martin; Chapperon, Matt; Chernikova, S.; Cohen, Bob; Cook, Fred J.; Cornish, Dudley T.; Correa, Anna; Commonweal; Con-Edison; Kings County
  - D, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Dangaloov, S.; Davis, Arthur K.; Davis, Ben; Dolsen, Jim; Drucker, H.; Dutt, [?]; Dilia Czechoslovak Theatrical and Literary Agency; Foreign Literature, Moscow; University of Vermont
  - E, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Eisenscher, Sigmund G.; Engelson, Joyce; Englestein, David; Evanier, Dave; Levy, Hyman; Abelard-Schuman Publishers
  - F, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Falck, G.; Feldman, Eugene; Felshin, Joe; Folsom, Dank; Frater, F.F.
  - G, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Gollobin, Esther; Goodlett
  - H, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    Heller, Abe; Hester, Hugh B.; Houtz, Philip; Hunton, Alphaeus; Huntington Library Quarterly; National Jewish Hospital at Denver
  - J, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Jeannette, [Heutoff?]; Jerome, Alice; Jerome, V.J.; Jonitis, Peter P.; Bates College
  - K, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Kanapa, Jean; Kaplan, Sidney; Kashton, Sidney; Kashton, W.; Kempton, Murray; Khan, Mohd. Shabbir; Kimura, Kikuya; Klugman, James; Labour-Progressive Party, Canada; Muslim Univerity, Aligarh, India; New York Post; La Nouvelle Critique
  - L, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Lamont, Dr.; Lamos, Al; Lapin, Adam; Lima, Mickie
  - M, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    Mandelblatt, Sol; Mansfield, Mike; Marzani, Carl; McGurty, Lawrence E.; Meyers, George; Morris, Leslie; Mumford, Charles J.; Cameron Associates; Labor-Progressive Party, Canada; Obelisk Book Store, Berkeley, Calif.; Southern Maryland Free State Library Association; USS Montana
  - N, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Noret, Paul; Nordholt, Wim; Ohlwerther, Geroge Lohr; Democratic Nouvelle; Novo Vreme, Sofia; Observateur, France
  - P - Q, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Patterson, William; Phillips, James K.; Pittman, John; Poon, John; Presser, J.; Quarles, Benjamin; Daily People's World; Morgan State College; People's Book Shop, Trinidad
  - R, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    Rivera, Diego; Roberts, Daniel; Robertson, Thomas; Rudich, Norman; Ryerson, Stanley; Wesleyan University
  - S, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    A.S.; Samah, B.C.; Saxe, Charlotte; Schappes, Morris U.; Scott, Edmund E.; Shenker, George; Simon, Walter; Sims?, Watt; Singletary, Prof.; Smith, Jessica; Sofronov, [?]; Sparks, Nenny; Stevenson, Phil; Suffin, Arnold; Stohr, R.A.; Wesleyan University
  - T, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    Tamai, Ryuzo; Thompson, Leona; Tkach, Tamara; Tiesler, Amy S.; Togai, Y.; Torichet, Francis; Tuckett, Angela; Labour Monthly; Toyo Keizai Shimpo Sha
  - w, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    Walker, Doris Briu; Weatherford, W.D.; Weeks, Edward; Wells, Dan; West, Jim; West, Mollie; Wilkerson, Doxey; Williamson, John; Winter, Carl; Winslow, Henry; Wolins, LeRoy; Atlantic Monthly; Berea College; Chicago Council of American-Soviet Friendship, Inc.
  - Y - Z, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Yuille, Clare; Zimmerman, E.F.; World News, London
  - A, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    Abot; Alleg, Gilberte; Allen, Jim; Aolu, Emmanuel Assan; Allen, George; Avery, David; Unwin, Ltd.; U.S. Dept. of the Army
  - B, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    Batterson, Warren; Baum, A.; Bencin, Miro; Benson, Robert; Bert, Eric; Bittleman; Blair, Nan; Blau, Patricia; Blum, Emanuel; Bonofsky, Phil; Bordages, Asa; Brownstone, Peter; Buckman, Rachel; Butler, A.; El Noticier del Brasil
  - C, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    Cammett, John M.; Canter, Harry; Cardiff, Ira D.; Catlett, Elizabeth; Charney, George; Chase, Homer B.; Chirko, Tom; Cochran, A. Burton; Cohen, Bob; Cohen, Jack; Community Party, London
  - D, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    Davis, Ben
  - E - F, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    Engleston, David; Ervin, Joseph B.; Ether, Vivian; Evans, Evan; Felshin, Joseph; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; Forrey, Bob; Foster, Bill; France, Clemens J.; Fund for Social Analysis; New Century Publishers
  - G, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    Gehmer, Evangeline; Gold, Mike; Goldman, Marius; Goodwon, Bob; Graham Du Bois, Shirley; Green, Edith; Greenfield, H.; Gustafson, B.G.
  - H - J, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    Healey, Dorothy; Hecht, Julius; Hellman, Beatrice; Hester, Hugh B.; Huitan, William; Ho, Phua Tjong; Hood, Robert; Howard, Milton; [H?], Abot; Hunton, Alphaeus; Johnson, Arnold; Johnson, Oakley
  - K, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    Keeney, M.J.; Keilsan; Kirlew, William E.; Kowal, Gertrude; Krchmarek, Anthony; Kuusinen, Hartta; Fund for Social Analysis; Sozialistiche Einheitspartei Deutschlands
  - L, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    Lakin, Bill; Lamont, Corliss; Landau, Saul; Lawson, Elizabeth; LaRose, John; LeSeur, Meridel; Loeser, Franz; Lofton, John; Lohr, George; Loper, L.E.; Lowenfels, Walter; Lubka, Lewis; Lukacs, George; Lumer, Hy
  - M, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    Maki, Erno J.; Mandelblatt, Sol; Meng Chi-ching; Metyolkin, Ivan; Morford, Richard; Morgan, John; Morris, Leslie; First Unitarian Church, South Bend, Ind.; Foreign Language Publishing House, Moscow; National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, Inc.; Obelisk Book Store; Peking Review
  - N - O, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    Novick, [?]; Overgaard, Andy
  - P, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    Palmer, J.E.; Pasternak, Boris; Patterson, William; Perlo, Vic; Perry, Rose; Pittman, John; Pratis, P.L.; Presser, J.; Daily Worker; Phylon; Pittsburgh Courier; Yale Review
  - R, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    Roberts, Holland; Rodell, Fred; Rossi, Victor; American Russian Institute; Yale Law School
  - S, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Schechter, Amy; Schnikind, [?]; Scott, Arthur S.; Selsam, Howard; Sharp, Geoff; Silver, Joseph; Simon, Brian; Simonson, David; Sklar, Martin J.; Sparks, Nemmy; Stefanovic, Sv.; Straus, Mark; Svoboda, F.; Szu-hsun, Meng; Suffin, Arnold; Sussman, Jeanette; Frederich Schiller Univ.; Institute of Diplomacy, Peking; Review of International Affairs, Belgrade; Statni Nakladatelstvi Politicke Literatury, Prague
  - T - U, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Takacs, G.; Takman, John; Taylor, SId; Thompson, Bob; Thompson, Elsa Knight; Thorner, Robert; Touchet, Frank; KPFA-FM, Berkeley; Legation of the Hungarian People's Republic, Washington, D.C.; Uruguay, XVII Congreso del Partido Comunista
  - W, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 3)